# 这牛肉酱绝了
This beef paste is absolutely delicious.
# 已经炒好的芝麻
Toasted sesame.
# 你说这酱能不香么
How can this possibly not smell wonderful?
# 我的天呐
Oh my god
# 香菇牛肉酱 您听听这声 咕嘟咕嘟
Shiitake Mushroom Beef Paste. You can hear – ‘GU-DU-GU-DU’
# 咱们选的这是带点肥肉的
The beef we select is the part with some fat,
# 这是牛腩这块 牛肉必须得煮
which is from beef brisket. Beef should be boiled first
# 猪肉你要是用五花肉
For pork, like pork belly,
# 生炒生煸就可以 牛肉不行
you can just do stir-fried with raw pork. But not beef
# 因为要是生煸的话
Because after stir fry,
# 它出来以后吃不动
beef will become tough
# 葱姜 凉水下锅
And add leek and ginger when water is still cool
# 脏的杂质 一点一点的
It will help to bring out those impurities
# 它就给激发出来了
Little by little
# 你要热的一下就激住了
Those impurities would not come out if you added the meat into hot water.
# 就封上了 再来点料酒
Then add some Chinese cooking wine.
# 虽然是小的细节 但是很重要
Though it sounds trivial, it is really important.
# 咱加点盐么 不加盐 现在煮着
Do we need to add some salt? –No, just boil it.
# 我看您这香菇都泡好了
I found the shiitake mushroom is ready now.
# 这水千万别糟蹋
Keep the water, do not waste it.
# 加油 香气一会就出来了
Add some oil. It should smell good soon.
# 煸香以后把香菇下锅
Add the mushroom after smelling the aroma.
# 这就烧会儿(加白水)
And boil it. (Add some water)
# 然后放点蚝油
Then put some oyster sauce.
# 把这个香菇一定要给它煨透了
The mushroom should be well-cooked.
# 它才好吃 才肉头
Then it will taste good and chewy.
# 放点黄酒 不煨透了有时候嚼不动
Otherwise, it will be too hard to chew. Add some huangjiu rice wine.
# 这沫子有了把沫子打干净
Skim off the scum
# 朝辉你看这香菇
Chaohui, come and look at the mushrooms.
# 圆圆乎乎胖胖乎乎的 就说明发透了
They become chubby, which means they are soaked well and ready.
# 这个时候吃着才肉头呢
They shall be chewy at this point.
# 其实中国菜的灵魂在于融合
Actually, the soul of Chinese cuisine is ‘fusion’.
# 它每个都单独处理
Each part of the dish has been processed separately
# 把它的味道都给加足了
and made flavorful as well.
# 这样它合在一块菜才好吃呢
Then the dish with all parts combined will become delicious.
# 焯完了 先把它捞出来
It is ready, let’s get the beef out.
# 拿出来也得用热水 别用凉水
Place them into hot water, but not cool water.
# 把牛肉搁里边 搁点葱姜
Add some leek and ginger with beef
# 料酒
Chinese cooking wine
# 搁点什么香料
And some spices
# 大料 草果 白蔻 香叶（干辣椒）
star anise, tsao-ko, white cardamom, bay leaf, (dried chili pepper)
# 一个白芷就行了
And just one baizhi should be good
# 盖盖20分钟
Cook for 20 minuets
# 香菇可以出锅了
Now we can remove the mushrooms from the pot
# 你看这个 跟小胖猪似的
See this one, it looks like a chubby pig
# 这水就吃满了 润
They are soaked with water totally. Moisturized
# 把香菇切成丁 这叫豌豆大的丁
Chop the mushrooms into pea-size
# 再大就是色子丁
For the size little bit bigger than this we called it dice-size.
# 行了 香菇也切完了  把酱兑出来吧
Okay, the chopped mushroom is ready. Let’s make the sauce.
# 甜面酱 一勺 两勺 三勺
Three spoons of "Tian Mian Jiang" (sweet bean paste)
# 再来一点（四勺
One more spoon. (Four spoons totally
# 豆瓣酱 一勺 两勺 三勺 四勺
Four spoons of Doubanjiang
# 这个酱炸酱特好吃
This sauce is super delicious
# 最后一个酱
One last Sause
# 一勺 两勺 这是蒜蓉辣酱
The chili garlic sauce
# 三勺 这也四勺
Also four spoons
# 肉好啦
Meat is ready
# 切成丁
Diced it
# 开炒了吧大爷
Da Ye, everything’s ready now, right?
# 花生油 搁点香油 这味立马出来了
Peanut oil, and some sesame oil. You can smell the aroma immediately
# 先把辣酱 蒜蓉辣酱放进去
First, we put the chili garlic sauce
# 这香味出来了
It smells good
# 再来点葱姜 这点要说一下
And some leek and ginger. And one thing to point out-
# 因为我们这肉是煮熟了的
Because we have our beef cooked already
# 就没必要提前下锅去煸炒
It is not necessary to stir fry the beef in advanced
# 如果是生肉的话 就要先煸肉
If you are using raw meat, you should stir fry it first
# 香菇 香菇粒 炒一下
Add the chopped mushroom
# 香菇也是要提前入味的
To get its flavor to deeply penetrate in advanced
# 甜面酱和豆瓣酱
Tian Mian Jiang and Doubanjiang
# 黄酒 把这盆涮涮
Rinse this pot with Huangjiu Rice Wine
# 搁里边去 不糟践
Then add it, without wasting anything
# 下肉 把肉放进去
And add the diced beef
# 这酱可精彩了 满满的牛肉粒
This wonderful paste now is filled with diced beef
# 把这香菇水下锅
Add the water we used to soak the mushroom
# 保持原有香菇的香味
To keep the original flavor of Shiitake Mushroom
# 来点老抽 冰糖老抽加出来是红亮的
Add some dark soy sauce. The color of this kind of dark soy sauce is bright and dark-red,
# 有的老抽加出来是黑的
while the color of some other dark soy sauces is black
# 所以咱们一般做菜的时候
So usually,
# 比较常用的这种冰糖老抽
we will prefer using this for cooking
# 且咕嘟着呢 您去俩歇着去吧
It is stewing. You two can take a break now.
# 我来看着这锅
Let me take care of this.
# 让它慢慢把这水咕嘟干了就行了
Let it stew slowly and be gooey
# 一直这锅里就冒着气泡
It is lightly boiling
# 咱们得把酱熬得稍微干一点
We want it to be thicker
# 把里边水分尽量让它熬出去
and reduce the water as much as possible
# 这样能够保存的时间长一点
It can help for longer storage
# 师父咱这酱快好了
Master, the sauce is nearly ready
# 再加点糖 十五克
Add 15g sugar
# 这酱马上就好了
It is almost done
# 咱们现在已经炒好的芝麻
And now we have the baked sesame
# 然后撒在里边 熟芝麻
Add to the paste. It is cooked sesame.
# 你说这酱能不香么
How can this possibly not smell wonderful?
# 我的天呐 怎么样
Oh my god. How is it?
# 香菇牛肉酱 您听听这声
Shiitake Mushroom Beef Paste. You can hear – ‘GU-DU-GU-DU’
# 行了 不能再炸了
Ok, don’t over fry it
# 好嘞 关火
Sure, turn the stove off now
# 大爷您看咱们这有中午的馒头
Da Ye, we have some Mantou (aka Chinese steamed buns) left here
# 我给您来一个
Let me get you one
# 大爷一天了 都没吃饭呢
Da Ye hasn’t eaten anything today till now
# 怎么样 我觉得比面条好吃
How is it? –I am feeling like it tastes even better than with noodles
# 给我师父来一个
Let me get one for master
# 这牛肉也不艮 还挺香
The beef is soft and smells good
# 这牛肉酱绝了
This beef paste is absolutely delicious.
# 咱今儿这酱也好 配比也好
The sauces we used are good, so as our ‘formula’
# 然后师父前期牛肉的处理也好
And beef processing method by the master is great too
# 完美
perfect
# 有网友请大爷二伯
One of our comments is
# 讲讲不同类型的醋
‘What is the difference between kinds of vinegar?’
# 咱们中国的比较有名的醋
In China, we have four famous types
# 四大类
of vinegar
# 北京的米醋
Beijing Rice vinegar
# 山西的陈醋
Shanxi Mature Aged Vinegar
# 镇江的香醋
Zhenjiang Vinegar
# 还有大红浙醋
As well as red vinegar
# 但是说还有好多地方的
Of course, there are more, like
# 还有四川的
those from Sichuan
# 还有山西的
or Shanxi
# 保宁醋
Baoning Vinegar
# 做宫保鸡丁用的
For kung pao chicken
# 对 做宫保鸡丁用的
Yeah for kung pao chicken
# 这类的地方醋
These kind of local vinegar
# 这也很多
are also popular
# 白醋和醋精是外来的
White vinegar and vinegar concentrate are imported
# 它色调的是纯白
They are pure white
# 尤其醋精特别酸
The vinegar concentrate, especially, is super sour
# 这用不好
For someone not good at using it
# 有时候做出这菜来
will make the dish
# 特别呛鼻子
smells sharp
# 一般我们要做糖醋汁
Usually when we were making the sweet and sour sauce
# 七十年代八十年代
in 70s or 80s
# 都用的是醋精
we used vinegar concentrate
# 用它呢 我们要早点熬
When using it, we should start stewing earlier
# 让这个醋挥发
And let the vinegar evaporate
# 把那种特别呛鼻的醋味
to remove the sharp smell
# 挥发出去
from the dishes
# 后来又出现了一个上海白醋
Then Shanghai white vinegar came out
# 白醋就比较稳定
The vinegar is more stable
# 他不是很酸
and not too sour
# 也就是离出锅
You can just add the white vinegar
# 你放里边
right before the dish out of pot
# 稍微的墩一下就可以了
and mildly cook for some more time
# 但是这些醋现在由于发酵
Now, most of the vinegar is fermented
# 还需要一个时间
It costs longer time
# 他跟酒是一样的
Just like liquor
# 他有多少度
It has its alcohol content
# 有的8度
Some are 8%
# 有的11度
Some are 11%
# 有13度
Some are 13%
# 有的能达到15度
And some can be up to 15%
# 为什么山西老陈醋
So why Shanxi Mature Aged Vinegar
# 就给大家感觉是比较有名
Is more famous
# 他要蹲三年五年八年
It is because it will take 3, 5, 8 years
# 十年
Or 10 years
# 醋越陈越好
The vinegar is better when it is aged
# 甚至那瓶有时候剩了多半瓶
Even when you have half bottle of vinegar left there
# 但是醋在用的时候就不好用了
It will become not as easy to use as at the beginning
# 我们要兑一些矿泉水
We can add some water
# 让他稍微稀释一下
To dilute it
# 要不太酸了
Otherwise it will be too sour
# 而且颜色非常重
And have very dark color
# 对 颜色非常重
Yeah, the color will be too dark
# 他不适合做菜
And not good for cooking
# 它适合调汁调味
But more for sauce and seasoning
# 香醋适合什么啊
And what about Zhenjiang Vinegar
# 吃闸蟹
Eat Chinese mitten crab
# 大闸蟹
For dipping sauce of Chinese mitten crab
# 都用的是香醋
Most of all choose Zhenjiang Vinegar
# 有的个别的
Some choose other
# 还用一些大红浙醋
Like red Vinegar
# 里边要加江米
And add some glutinous rice
# 这个香醋
Zhenjiang Vinegar
# 它发甜
Is sweet
# 一般咱们吃饺子
When we eat dumplings
# 吃馅饼
Or meat pies
# 都用香醋
We will use Zhenjiang Vinegar
# 它不是很酸
It is not too sour
# 而且醋的味道比较稳定
and has stable flavor
# 现在我们因为文化交流
Because of cultural exchanging,
# 很多外国来的产品
many products from other countries
# 也很多
There are a lot,
# 叫苹果醋
like apple cider vinegar
# 用各种的水果做的醋
or vinegar made of different fruits
# 一般都是做大拌菜
Most of them are for salad
# 那个醋
Those vinegar
# 特别稳定
Are really stable
# 酸味特别润
Has super smooth sour,
# 它不是很呛鼻子
no sharp smell
# 而且它能味道很稳定
and stable flavor
# 他不会失掉一份
It will keep its own flavor in the dish
# 所以有好多做菜当中
So many chefs
# 做一些凉拌菜
Will use fruit vinegar
# 都用果醋
for salads
# 基本上我们国家这些醋
So these vinegars are basically what we have in China
# 基本都是这样
Basically like this